const questions = [
    {
        question: "Which organel is the powerhouse of the cell?",
        optionA: "Golgi",
        optionB: "Endoplasmatic reticulum",
        optionC: "Mitochondria",
        optionD: "Nucleus",
        correctOption: "optionC"
    },

    {
        question: "Which is the most common type of Arthritis",
        optionA: "Gout",
        optionB: "Osteoarthritis",
        optionC: "Rheumatoid Arthritis",
        optionD: "Psoriatic Arthritis",
        correctOption: "optionB"
    },

    {
        question: "How much time does it take for an E.coli cell to replicate?",
        optionA: "30 minutes",
        optionB: "20 minutes",
        optionC: "1 hour",
        optionD: "12 hours",
        correctOption: "optionB"
    },

    {
        question: "__ has the biggest number of chromosomes.",
        optionA: "Corn",
        optionB: "Humans",
        optionC: "African Hedgehog",
        optionD: "Fruit Fly",
        correctOption: "optionC"
    },

    {
        question: "The word NOUS in Greek means...",
        optionA: "Mind",
        optionB: "Thought",
        optionC: "Unity",
        optionD: "Alive",
        correctOption: "optionA"
    },

    {
        question: "Where is the smallest bone in human body located?",
        optionA: "Toes",
        optionB: "Ears",
        optionC: "Fingers",
        optionD: "Nose",
        correctOption: "optionB"
    },

    {
        question: "Rhizobia are bacteria known for fixing what type of gas?",
        optionA: "Nitrogen",
        optionB: "Carbon Dioxide",
        optionC: "Oxygen",
        optionD: "Hydrogen",
        correctOption: "optionA"
    },

    {
        question: "Who discovered bacteria in 1674?",
        optionA: "Francesco Redi",
        optionB: "Robert Koch",
        optionC: "Antoni van Leeuwenhoek",
        optionD: "Louis Pasteur",
        correctOption: "optionC"
    },

    {
        question: "Which chemical inside the nucleus of a cell carries the genetic instructions for making living organisms?",
        optionA: "DNA",
        optionB: "Nucleolus",
        optionC: "Cytoplasm",
        optionD: "Nucleoplasm",
        correctOption: "optionA"
    },

    {
        question: "How many blood cells are destroyed every second in the human body?",
        optionA: "5 million",
        optionB: "20 billion",
        optionC: "30 million",
        optionD: "15 million",
        correctOption: "optionD"
    },

    {
        question: "What allows plants to absorb energy from light?",
        optionA: "Chroloplast",
        optionB: "Chlorophyl",
        optionC: "Stem",
        optionD: "Leaves",
        correctOption: "optionB"
    },

    {
        question: "The first biotechnology patent was for a microorganism used to clean up what?",
        optionA: "Oil spills",
        optionB: "Vacuum cleaners",
        optionC: "Bedrooms",
        optionD: "Cafeterias",
        correctOption: "optionA"
    },

    {
        question: "One of the most famous examples of the practical use of synthetic biology was the modification of E. coli and yeast to produce a drug to fight what disease?",
        optionA: "Scurvy",
        optionB: "Rickets",
        optionC: "Cancer",
        optionD: "Malaria",
        correctOption: "optionD"
    },

    {
        question: "Who received the Nobel Prize in Chemistry in 1993 for inventing PCR?",
        optionA: "David Baltimore",
        optionB: "Kary Mullis",
        optionC: "Robert Weinberg",
        optionD: "John Nash",
        correctOption: "optionB"
    },

    {
        question: "What does the acronym PCR stand for?",
        optionA: "Polymerase Chain Reaction",
        optionB: "Polymerase Copying Reaction",
        optionC: "Polymerase Copied Repeats",
        optionD: "Polymerase Chain Restoration",
        correctOption: "optionA"
    },

    {
        question: "Nucleotide triphosphates (dNTPs) are added to the growing DNA strand during the _______________ phase. ",
        optionA: "Extension/elongation",
        optionB: "Annealing",
        optionC: "Denaturation/separation",
        optionD: "Preparation",
        correctOption: "optionA"
    },

    {
        question: "Where does DNA replication take place?",
        optionA: "Cytoplasm",
        optionB: "Ribosome",
        optionC: "Nucleus",
        optionD: "Golgi Body",
        correctOption: "optionC"
    },

    {
        question: "The process of making mRNA from DNA is called:",
        optionA: "Replication",
        optionB: "Protein synthesis",
        optionC: "Translation",
        optionD: "Transcription",
        correctOption: "optionD"
    },

    {
        question: "A triplet of mRNA is called:",
        optionA: "codon",
        optionB: "amino acid",
        optionC: "anticodon",
        optionD: "peptide bond",
        correctOption: "optionA"
    },

    {
        question: "DNA consists of bases. What holds the base pairs together?",
        optionA: "peptide bonds",
        optionB: "hydrogen bonds",
        optionC: "ionic bonds",
        optionD: "covalent bonds",
        correctOption: "optionB"
    },

    {
        question: "The enzyme that catalyzes the synthesis of new DNA molecules is called:",
        optionA: "DNA ligase",
        optionB: "DNA gyrase",
        optionC: "DNA polymerase",
        optionD: "DNA helicase",
        correctOption: "optionC"
    },

    {
        question: "Which of the following is NOT a component of nucleic acids?",
        optionA: "nitrogen bases",
        optionB: "protein",
        optionC: "phosphate",
        optionD: "sugar",
        correctOption: "optionB"
    },

    {
        question: "The double helix DNA model was proposed by:",
        optionA: "Watson and Crick",
        optionB: "Griffith",
        optionC: "Avery",
        optionD: "Beadle and Tatum",
        correctOption: "optionA"
    },

    {
        question: "If a short sequence of DNA is AATTGCCGT, its complement is:",
        optionA: "AAAACDCCA",
        optionB: "TTAACGGCT",
        optionC: "TTAACGGCA",
        optionD: "TTAAGCCGA",
        correctOption: "optionC"
    },

    {
        question: "The function of tRNA is to:",
        optionA: "provide a place for protein synthesis",
        optionB: "transport amino acids to the ribosome",
        optionC: "travel to the ribosome to direct protein synthesis",
        optionD: "none of these is correct",
        correctOption: "optionB"
    },

    {
        question: "Amino acids are the building blocks of:",
        optionA: "DNA and RNA",
        optionB: "lipids",
        optionC: "proteins",
        optionD: "carbohydrates",
        correctOption: "optionC"
    }

]

// save the selected questions out of all available questions
var shuffledQuestions = [] 

// shuffle and choose 10 random questions 
function handleQuestions() { 
    
    while (shuffledQuestions.length <= 9) {
        const random = questions[Math.floor(Math.random() * questions.length)]

        if (!shuffledQuestions.includes(random)) {
            shuffledQuestions.push(random)
        }
    }
}

var questionNumber = 1;  // current question number
var playerScore = 0;     // player score
var wrongAttempt = 0;    // number of wrong answers 
var indexNumber = 0;     // counter to display next question

// display next question 
// display player and quiz information 
function nextQuestion(index) {

    handleQuestions()
    const currentQuestion = shuffledQuestions[index];

    document.getElementById("question-number").innerHTML = questionNumber;
    document.getElementById("player-score").innerHTML = playerScore;
    document.getElementById("display-question").innerHTML = currentQuestion.question;
    document.getElementById("option-one-label").innerHTML = currentQuestion.optionA;
    document.getElementById("option-two-label").innerHTML = currentQuestion.optionB;
    document.getElementById("option-three-label").innerHTML = currentQuestion.optionC;
    document.getElementById("option-four-label").innerHTML = currentQuestion.optionD;
}

function checkForAnswer() {
    const currentQuestion = shuffledQuestions[indexNumber]       //gets current question 
    const currentQuestionAnswer = currentQuestion.correctOption; //gets current question's answer
    const options = document.getElementsByName("option");        //gets all options of a question
    var correctOption = null;

    options.forEach((option) => {
        if (option.value === currentQuestionAnswer) {
            
            // correct radio input with correct answer
            correctOption = option.labels[0].id;
        }
    })

    // check if a radio input has been checked 
    //          or an option has been chosen
    if (options[0].checked === false && 
        options[1].checked === false && 
        options[2].checked === false && 
        options[3].checked == false) {
        document.getElementById('option-modal').style.display = "flex";
    }

    //check if checked radio button is same as the correct answer
    options.forEach((option) => {
        if (option.checked === true && option.value === currentQuestionAnswer) {
            document.getElementById(correctOption).style.backgroundColor = "#71c93ecb";
            playerScore++; // increase player's score
            indexNumber++; // increase index to display next question
            
            // delay change of question number util the next question loads
            setTimeout(() => {
                questionNumber++;
            }, 1000);
        }

        else if (option.checked && option.value !== currentQuestionAnswer) {
            const wrongLabelId = option.labels[0].id;
            document.getElementById(wrongLabelId).style.backgroundColor = "#e74747b4";
            document.getElementById(correctOption).style.backgroundColor = "#71c93ecb";
            wrongAttempt++; //adds 1 to wrong attempts 
            indexNumber++;

            // delay change of question number util the next question loads
            setTimeout(() => {
                questionNumber++;
            }, 1000);
        }
    })
}

// next question button
function handleNextQuestion() {

    checkForAnswer(); //check if answer is right or wrong 
    clearRadioButtons();

    setTimeout(() => {
        if (indexNumber <= 9) {
            nextQuestion(indexNumber);
        }
        else {
            endGame();
        }

        resetOptionColor();
    }, 1000);
}

//sets option colors to null after displaying the right/wrong colors
function resetOptionColor() {
    const options = document.getElementsByName("option");
    options.forEach((option) => {
        document.getElementById(option.labels[0].id).style.backgroundColor = "";
    })
}

// clear radio buttons for next question
function clearRadioButtons() {
    const options = document.getElementsByName("option");
    for (let i = 0; i < options.length; i++) {
        options[i].checked = false;
    }
}

// game finished - function
function endGame() {

    let remark = null;
    let remarkColor = null;

    // display player feedback according to score
    if (playerScore <= 3) {
        remark = "Not so good. Keep Practicing!";
        remarkColor = "red";
    }
    else if (playerScore >= 4 && playerScore < 7) {
        remark = "Okay. You can do better!";
        remarkColor = "orange";
    }
    else if (playerScore >= 7) {
        remark = "Amazing! Keep up the good work.";
        remarkColor = "green";
    }

    const playerGrade = (playerScore / 10) * 100;

    // score board
    document.getElementById('remarks').innerHTML = remark;
    document.getElementById('remarks').style.color = remarkColor;
    document.getElementById('grade-percentage').innerHTML = playerGrade;
    document.getElementById('wrong-answers').innerHTML = wrongAttempt;
    document.getElementById('right-answers').innerHTML = playerScore;
    document.getElementById('score-modal').style.display = "flex";

}

// 1. close score modal
// 2. reset game 
// 3. reshuffle questions

function resetScore() {
    questionNumber = 1;
    playerScore = 0;
    wrongAttempt = 0;
    indexNumber = 0;
    shuffledQuestions = [];
    nextQuestion(indexNumber);
    document.getElementById('score-modal').style.display = "none";
}

//function to close warning modal
function closeWarning() {
    document.getElementById('option-modal').style.display = "none"
}